Good afternoon. Today's דף daf is נג, Nun-Gimel, 53. We pick up
at about 20 lines from the bottom. We are in the middle
of a discussion about some aspects relating to שמיטה, Shmita, specifically the
obligation that once basically
during שמיטה, Shmita, all of the food is treated as ownerless and
people are free to go ahead and collect it or, but also
the wealthy as well, it's a free-for-all for everyone. So you collect
some of the food and you bring it into your house, you
don't eat everything right away. But then keeping food in your house
for too long of a time contradicts some of the ethos of
שמיטה Shmita because it's basically then it's sort of like you're owning
it and you're protecting it and you're acting as though as though
it's not sort of everyone's food, it's only yours. You're hoarding the
food in your home. So the rabbis understand that once there is
no longer food available out in the field of this type, like
if you are hoarding the apples, if you're storing apples in your
home, as long as there's apples out in the field for anybody
to take, you can have some apples in your home. But once
there's no longer anything available, it says ולחיה אשר בארצך v’lachaya asher
b’artzecha for the wild animal ולחיה אשר בארצך, v’lachaya asher b’artzecha,
then you can't keep them in your home as well. You have
to bring them out and you have to do ביעור, biur, destroying.
רש"י Rashi says destroying basically means just putting them out there for
the animals, but תוספות Tosafot quotes other sources that make it clear
that it really is distributing them equally amongst the poor and amongst
everybody and you can actually also you put them out and you
say, 'Here are two bushels of apples,' and everybody comes and takes,
you could also take a few back but you can't keep them
all to yourself. That's called ביעור. biur. ביעור biur has to be
done when that מין, min, that type of food that you're having
in your house is no longer available as I said to the
animals that are out in the field. The גמרא Gemara ended yesterday
by saying that there were three areas for ביעור: biur: יהודה, Yehuda,
גליל, Galil, and עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, Judea, the Galilee, and עבר
הירדן. Ever HaYarden. And when there was and any time there's some
food left in like some apples somewhere in יהודה, Yehuda, even if
where you live in יהודה Yehuda there are no apples, that's okay,
somewhere in יהודה Yehuda there are apples. But once there's no apples
anywhere in יהודה, Yehuda, then you have to if you're living in
יהודה Yehuda you have to get them out of your house. And
the same by those other regions. And then the גמרא Gemara ended
yesterday, all this was a digression from the issue about practices where
you came from, practices where you're going. Before you came from there
were no longer apples but where you're going there are, or vice-versa.
And then the last story in the גמרא, Gemara, which is just
worth repeating, is a discussion about let's say you're taking apples with
you from Israel and you left Israel and you realize you have
some apples on
you and it's the time of ביעור. biur. So what do you
do? Do you get rid of them now that you're in Cincinnati
or what do you do? So there's a debate. Some say yeah,
you distribute them wherever you are. And other says no, it says
בארצך, b’artzecha, that they have to be distributed to those in the
land. So you actually have to fly them back to Israel and
distribute them in Israel. So the גמרא Gemara ended with a great
story that who was it that
רב ספרא, Rav Safra, right, was leaving Israel and he realized he
had a מפלך miflakh of wine and he asked his two students
who were with him, 'How do we פסקן? pasken? Do you have
a tradition how we פסקן?' pasken? The two rabbis who were with
him.
So one said, 'Yeah, we פסקן pasken you have to go back
to Israel.' And the other said, 'No, no, we פסקן pasken you
don't have to go back to Israel.' So he says, 'Oh good,
I go by the second פסק, psak, the one that you don't
have to go back to Israel.' And he claimed it was because
he believed that that person had a more trustworthy tradition. But רב
יוסף Rav Yosef ended and I just have to read the פסוק
pasuk again because it's such a great line. So קרי ליה רב
יוסף, korei lei Rav Yosef, it starts here with this little circle
at the beginning of the line about 20 lines from the bottom,
עמי בעצו ישאל ומקלו יגיד לו. Ami b’atzo yishal umaklo yagid lo.
My people, this is the פסוק pasuk that refers
to like necromancy and fortune-telling, 'My people ask their stick and their
staff will tell them,' like the future. But he does a little
play on words: ומקלו יגיד לו, umaklo yagid lo, the staff, מקל,
makel, כל המקל מגיד לו. kol hamekel magid lo.
Anybody who is going to be lenient to him, that's the one
he wants to tell him what the הלכה halacha is. Okay, so
anyway, but that's where we are in the middle of discussions of
ביעור. biur. And now we continue. רבי אלעאי Rebbi Ilai פץ כסניתא
דשביעית. patz kasnisa d’shvi’is. רבי אלעאי Rebbi Ilai cut down a palm
branch on שמיטה Shmita and this was a branch that had on
it כסניתא kasnisa refers to a branch that had on it unripe
dates.
The dates were not edible yet at this stage and they were
going to go to waste. So היכי עביד הכי, heichi avid hachi,
how are you allowed to do that? לאכלה אמר רחמנא, l'ochla amar
Rachmana, it says that all of the produce should be for
eating ולא להפסד v'lo l'hefseid and not to go to waste. So
by cutting down the branch when these dates are still at this
stage... stage that you're wasting them. וכי תימא הני מילי v'atima hani
milei היכא דנחית לפירא heicha d'nachis l'peira maybe that's only once the
fruit has got I mean you could use the branch for firewood
that's not a waste of the branch but it's a waste of
the dates. So maybe you could say ah the idea of not
wasting the dates as the fruit the produce is once it's already
is considered a fruit. אבל היכא דלא נחית לפירא aval heicha d'lo
nachis l'peira here they're unripe they're small maybe they're not yet considered
a fruit. No there's no problem about cutting down the branch even
if these unripe fruit are going to waste because they're not yet
considered down so that they would then ripen into dates.
Well actually that's a good guess we're going to say that in
the end but at this stage we think no we think he's
cutting it down because he wants to use the branch for firewood
and he doesn't care about the fact that there's some unripe dates
on the branch. So the Gemara says how could he do that?
So if you say it's because the dates were not yet ripened.
ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה v'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha הני מתחלי דערלה hani matchli d'orlah
these are like מתחלי matchli which are like shells of dates.
Sorry what did he cut down?
He cut down a palm branch
to use
for firewood and they had little clusters of dates of unripe dates
on them. Okay. So Rav Nachman says in the name of Rabbah
bar Avuha these מתחלי matchli these like which are like shells over
like some type of you know exterior protective growth that grows around
unripe dates of ערלה orlah are אסורי assuri forbidden they're also considered
ערלה. orlah. הואיל ונעשו שומר לפירא hoil v'nasu shomer l'pira since they
protect the fruit they're considered like the fruit and they also have
a status of ערלה. orlah. ושומר לפירא אימת הוי v'shomer l'pira eimat
havei so the Gemara says when are they protecting the fruit? בקופרי
bekufri when the dates are still unripe that's when they have this
the this protective shell and then as they continue to ripen it
falls off. Not having watched dates ripen I can't report on that
but anyway that's I'm trusting Rashi. So look it's considered to be
a part of the fruit and it only exists when the fruit
is unripe. You see that when the fruit is unripe the fruit
itself is considered a fruit even if it's in its unripe state.
Because because ערלה orlah only applies to fruit and he's only applying
ערלה orlah to the protector of the fruit so when and that
you know because it's an extension of the fruit itself but he's
considering the date a fruit even in its unripe state.
וקקרי להו פירי v'ka kari lehu peiri so he's considered the even
unripe date to be a fruit and if it's true by ערלה
orlah presumably it should be true by שביעית. shvi'is. So the Gemara
says Rav Nachman you're right. Rav Nachman does treat it like a
fruit at an unripe stage but that's like one opinion. היא דאמר
כרבי יוסי hi d'amar k'Rabbi Yosi he's going like Rabbi Yosi who
considers an unripe fruit to be a fruit at least by ערלה.
orlah. דתנן התם d'tnan hatam דתנן d'tnan Rabbi Yosi אומר סמדר אסור
מפני שהוא פרי omer smadar assur mipnei shehu peiri סמדר smadar which
is the very beginning of the fruit of a grape is forbidden
because of ערלה orlah it's already considered a fruit at that early
stage. So fine there are opinions that things are considered fruit at
an early stage. ופליגי רבנן עליה u'pligi rabbanan alei דרבי יוסי d'Rabbi
Yosi but we'll posit that there are Rabbis the the Rabbis argue
on Rabbi Yosi it's not a unanimous opinion and would say that
things are only considered fruit relative to ערלה orlah for שמיטה shmita
when they ripen and again that's how
רב אילעאי Rav Ila'i could cut down that branch because he goes
like the more lenient approach and it's not yet fruit until a
later stage.
What about just in general like not wanting to בל תשחית? bal
tashchis? What what's he doing?
He's making firewood. Why בל תשחית? bal tashchis? You're allowed to cut
down branches for firewood.
And what shouldn't he cut down one that doesn't have fruit on
it?
This was the available one. Okay. Now the Gemara says very harsh
view on בל תשחית. bal tashchis. So the Gemara says ומי פליגי
רבנן עליה דרבי יוסי u'mi pligi rabbanan alei d'Rabbi Yosi do the
Rabbis really argue on Rabbi Yosi בשאר אילנות bish'ar ilanos by other
things other than grapes? You've said a debate by grapes סמדר smadar
or later stage. But by other trees including our date tree that
we're talking about there's not really a debate and certainly not a
debate that would say that this stage here is not considered to
be a fruit. והתנן vehatnan we taught in a Mishnah מאימתי אין
קוצצין את האילנות בשביעית me'eimatai ein kotzetzin es ha'ilanos bishvi'is here's exactly
our
case. So funny the Gemara didn't jump right to that. At what
stage can you not cut down branches on שביעית shvi'is because of
the fruit on it and it would be considered wasting the fruit?
ממש mamash the exact case that we're dealing with. Forget ערלה. orlah.
בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim כל האילנות משיוציאו kol ha'ilanos misheyotziu
all of the trees as soon as the fruit begins to emerge
then even if it's completely unripe as soon as there's a fruit
then you can no longer cut down the branch that's bearing that
fruit. ובית הלל אומרים u'Veis Hillel omrim Beis Hillel says החרובים משישרשו
hacharuvim misheyishreshu the carobs from the time they that does not mean
they get roots but משישלשלו misheyishaleshalu here means meaning they become braided
like a שרשרת sharsheres okay so apparently as the it's a certain
stage in the development of the fruit והגפנים משיגריעו vehagfanim misheyagriu the
the grapes from the time they begin to grow a little bit
okay that's הגריעו agriu that's just a phrase referring to a little
bit of growth not just not the moment they
emerge והזיתים משינצו vehazeisim misheyinetzu olives from the time they flower apparently
there's like a flowering and a budding around you know around the
olive ושאר כל האילנות משי v'sh'ar kol ha'ilanos meshi and all other
trees
from Okay, so בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai
only disagree with three trees: carob, grape, and olives. Everything else they
agree it's considered a fruit for שמיטה Shemita purposes and you can't
waste it as soon as the fruit emerges. Now, and the גמרא
Gemara is going to go further to say that this בית הלל
Beit Hillel is exactly the rabbis that argue on רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. ואמר רב אסי, Va'amar Rav Assi, and now Rav Assi says
הוא בוסר, hu boser, the stage we call בוסר boser which is
unripe, הוא גירוע hu girua is the same phrase referred to as
by בית הלל Beit Hillel of the גירוע girua of the grapes.
So it says when the grapes begin to are a little bigger,
not סמדר, smadar, not that they've just emerged, a little bigger, that
stage that בית הלל Beit Hillel is referring to is a stage
that elsewhere is referred to as בוסר, boser, which is also unripe
but a little developed. הוא פול הלבן, Hu pul halavan, and that's
also the white bean. Okay, the פול הלבן pul halavan has a
lot of play in various areas of agriculture הלכה. halacha. So the
גמרא Gemara says פול הלבן סלקא דעתך? pul halavan salka daatach? What
do you mean? It's a grape, what do you mean it's a
white bean? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אימא שהוא כפול הלבן,
ella eima shehu kepul halavan, the size of it is when it
gets to be the size of this white bean. Anyway, ומאן שמעת
ליה דאמר בוסר אין סמדר לא? uman shamata lei de'amar boser in
smadar lo? When we so now we have בית הלל Beit Hillel
saying it goes by the grapes go by משיגריעו. misheyagri'u. And בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says סמדר. smadar. So again this משיגריעו misheyagri'u is
a little bit bigger, it's the stage called בוסר. boser. So who
is the one that says this? So that's רבנן, rabbanan, that's the
same rabbis you said רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose you know says that
it's סמדר smadar already it's a problem. Okay so that and but
the rabbis who argue on him say not סמדר, smadar, they say
בוסר. boser. Well בוסר, boser, that's the position that בית הלל Beit
Hillel says. וקתני Uketani שאר כל האילנות משהוציאו. shear kol ha'ilanot misheyotzi'u.
So this was a little complicated, but the basic point was בית
הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai disagree by שביעית. Shevi'it.
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says as soon as the thing emerges. בית
הלל Beit Hillel says you know for a handful of things like
grapes and olives and carobs, it's a little bit later. So the
גמרא Gemara says fine, so that idea of a little bit later
by grapes that parallels the rabbis who argue on רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. And what we do see is there might be some disagreement
about grapes or about carobs or about olives, but everybody agrees that
all other trees as soon as the fruit emerges it's a problem.
So how again back to the story of רבי אלעאי, Rabbi Ilai,
how could he cut down those palm trees if everybody agrees certainly
by שביעית Shevi'it that it's considered a fruit by these other trees
as soon as it emerges and you can't waste it? So how
could he just cut down this palm tree, this palm branch?
I understand that it makes sense to read it this way, nobody
says up until this moment, including רש"י Rashi I mean, that he
was cutting it down for the wood.
Nobody says it explicitly, רש"י Rashi assumes that's what it was, that's
what he was doing.
Does he say that?
I looked and I maybe I missed it, hold
on.
I find it hard to penetrate the assumption sometimes.
Yeah, רש"י, Rashi, the first wide line, קץ כפנייתא דשביעית, katz kafniyota
deshvi'it, דקל טעון כפניית, dekel ta'un kafniyot, והן תמרים קטנים שלא בשלו,
vehen tmarim ktanim shelo bishlu, וקצץ הדקל לעצים. vekatzat hadekel le'etzim.
Oh, there you go, thank you.
Okay, והשיר כפניית. vehishir kafniyot. Okay, yeah.
That's an incredibly important detail.
Yeah, but the point is it wasn't בל תשחית bal tashchit on
the wood, but what are you doing ignoring the fruit? Exactly.
No, but it's incredibly important, cut it for the wood and the
שאלה shayla is on the fruit.
Right, how could you cut it for the wood and let the
fruit go to waste? And maybe there's a stage where the fruit
is inconsequential is the question, it's not yet an object that you
have to relate to. And the גמרא Gemara says no, as soon
as it emerges we see here it's considered a fruit and you
have to deal with its קדושת שביעית kedushat shevi'it and you can't
say it's incidental. Let's see the answer. So back to the גמרא,
Gemara, גמרא Gemara says like this,
אלא רבי אלעאי בדניסכני קץ. ella Rabbi Ilai bediniskhani katz. He cut
down the male palm trees or
branches of male palm tree or the tree itself. Now palm trees
actually I don't know if people know are actually come in a
gender, come in male and female variety, and the male ones the
fruits on it never really ripen and get beyond a small stage.
And what they if you do want them to ripen, they don't
ripen on the tree, you actually רש"י Rashi says you pick the
fruit and you put them in branches made out of out of
palm, what's it called, the things made out of palm, not wicker,
what are the, what do you move palm
leaves? Fronds? Whatever, no, but when you weave them don't they have
a name? Anyway, anyway baskets made out of
woven palm leaves and that actually you keep them in that basket
and then they ripen after they're picked. There are some fruit that
only fully ripen after they're picked.
Pears? Right, so basically the answer was exactly as Dov suggested, yeah,
he wasn't wasting anything, he cuts it down, he picks the fruit
and it'll ripen afterwards, so no problem.
branch down too, which he used for firewood.
Would you use for firewood? Okay. So that was a little bit
now that we're talking about fruit of שביעית, Shvi'is, it talked about
this issue about, you know, the fruit and going to waste, but
again, the major theme is the theme of ביעור Biyur of once
it's too late to have to once it's no longer out in
the field, have to take it out of your house. Yes. I'm
sorry, Eli had his hand up.
Yeah. We just had the prohibition of cutting down fruit trees when
you're at war. Right. So this is all going to not apply
if
you're in a city besieging the city.
Right. Well, that's an interesting question about, you know, we take this
פסוק Pasuk about the fruit trees and we more make a larger
prohibition about בל תשחית, Bal Tashchis, which I don't want to focus
now on discussing all of the parameters. But,
you know, the difference would be is that it's pretty hard to
be עובר Over on בל תשחית Bal Tashchis because even though your
parents will say things like, you know, oh, eat all the food
on your plate, if there's food on your plate it's בל תשחית,
Bal Tashchis, בל תשחית Bal Tashchis is like wanton destruction without any
purpose, without serving any goal. Right. So for example, the גמרא Gemara
says if somebody wants to, you know,
break something as a way of venting their anger, it's not בל
תשחית Bal Tashchis because they're using it to vent their anger. So
it's very hard to be עובר Over on בל תשחית Bal Tashchis
as totally wanton destruction. So to measure whether cutting down a tree
that has some fruit on it would be בל תשחית Bal Tashchis
would be, look, if right, if this is a good use of
this tree, you need firewood, and you know, there's no other good
available tree for firewood or whatever, right, so it's not בל תשחית.
Bal Tashchis. You know, but that's a different question than yes, but
looking at the more macro, the fruit is going to waste, you
know. But the בל תשחית Bal Tashchis more sort of looks a
little I mean, looks at the micro. But the בל תשחית Bal
Tashchis looks more at the macro, right? And the בל תשחית Bal
Tashchis basically says, you know, what's this a legitimate use of the
tree? And if the answer is yes, then it's not a בל
תשחית. Bal Tashchis. Okay? Whereas this question is more of a micro
question. The fruit has קדושת שביעית Kedushas Shvi'is and you and they
weren't achieving their potential. They were not being used, you know, in
the way they needed to be used.
But there definitely is a difference between those. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Where are we? תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now
back to the idea of ביעור. Biyur. אוכלין בענבים עד שיכלו דליות
של אכל Ochlin Ba'anavim Ad Sheyichlu Dalyos Shel Ochel or אבל, Avel,
רש״י Rashi has a גרסא, Girsa, name of a place, it doesn't
mean food. You can eat grapes until there's no longer on the
trellises in this place called אבל, Avel, which apparently was a place
where grapes could be found
the latest in the season. So this is going to back to
the point that even if they're found somewhere else, as long as
it's within the same huge region of יהודה Yehuda or גליל, Galil,
you know, even if there's not in your immediate geographic area, you're
okay. So you can eat the grapes as long as there are
some still on the trellises in אבל, Avel, let's say that's it.
אם יש מאוחרות מהם, Im Yesh Me'ucharos Meihem, but now it's actually
making this point. You know, we discussed before about the whole thing
about מצה, Matzah, about inspection versus a quantifiable thing of eighteen minutes.
So here it says, don't get me wrong, is the ברייתא Braisa
essentially saying. It's not really determined by the grapes in this place.
It really that's just a good rule of thumb because this is
the place that usually grapes can be found the latest in the
season. But if there are grapes that are found that are later
than them and that are still out in the field, אוכלין עליהם,
Ochlin Aleihem, then you rely on those other later grapes for the
real rule is you rely on as long as there's something still
out there somewhere. Don't think that these ideas are that the names
we're giving here is is limiting, it's just giving a general rule
of thumb. אוכלין בזיתים עד שיכלה אחרון
שבתקוע. Ochlin Bazayisim Ad Sheyichleh Acharon Shebitkoa. You can eat olives until
there's no olives left in תקוע. Tekoa. רבי אליעזר אומר עד שיכלה
אחרון של גוש חלב, Rabbi Eliezer Omer Ad Sheyichleh Acharon Shel Gush
Chalav, until there's none left in גוש חלב, Gush Chalav, apparently he
believes that there they were available even later. כדי, Kedei, now how
many olives have to be left? What, is one olive enough? כדי
שעני יוצא ואינו מוצא לא בנופו ולא בעיקרו רובע. Kedei She'ani Yotzei
V'eino Motzei Lo Benofo V'lo Be'ikaro Rova. So it has to be
so few olives left that a poor person would not be able
to go out and find neither
in the branches nor in the root, meaning neither on the tree
or fallen to the ground, a רובע, Rova, like a quart. Okay.
So once there's not even a quart to be found anywhere, then
it's considered there are no olives left and if you have olives
in your house you have to get rid of them. אוכלין בגרוגרות
עד שיכלו פגי בית היני. Ochlin Bigrogeros Ad Sheyichlu Pagei Beis Hini.
You can eat pressed figs until the ones from this until those
in בית היני Beis Hini are no longer available. Okay. So now
what I have to tell you I don't understand here is the
idea of גרוגרות, Grogeros, like dried figs. רש״י Rashi says תאנים יבשים.
Te'einim Yeveishim. So I have to say I don't get it exactly
because you are with if you eat until it's no longer available
on the trees, what's on the trees aren't dried figs, they're fresh
figs. But presumably what it means is that you You picked the
figs, you brought them into your home, you dried them out, imagine
like prunes or raisins, right? So they'll last a long time, and
you can eat them until there are no longer fresh figs available
on the trees, right? But it's a little bit funny that it's
talking about you eating dried figs and it's determined by as long
as there are fresh figs available on the trees.
I think figs, dry figs, they do not ripen all at once,
okay, during one season. Figs ripen over a long period of time.
So that's why the point is you might have them dried and
they're lasting a long time. Exactly. That's a very thank you, that's
very helpful.
So that happens to be unique to figs.
Interesting. Okay, so that's very helpful. That explains why here we're mentioning
dried, because the other stuff you would eat fresh and then by
the time it wasn't out in the field, you know, you would
still be, you could still be eating them at home. But by
the figs, as Dov just pointed out, if they ripen over many
different periods of times, so we you could be eating them from
nine months ago, but the reason you're eating them is because you
dried them out. So you're eating your dried figs and you can
eat them until there's none left in
בית היני. Beit Hini. So אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda לא
הותרו lo hutru פגי בית היני. pagei Beit Hini. Now פגים pagim
also means like small ones. So this first statement was saying that
even the small ones in בית היני Beit Hini are considered to
be again this issue of considered fruit, and as long as they're
still there, you can still eat the stuff you had from months
ago. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says no, we did not mention
those small figs in בית היני Beit Hini אלא ella in מעשר,
Ma'aser, only for laws of מעשר. Ma'aser. What was the statement? פגי
בית היני ואהיני דטובנא. pagei Beit Hini ve'ahini deTuvina. So the פגים,
pagim, these small figs of בית היני, Beit Hini, and the אהיני
ahini of,
which are the dates of טובנא, Tuvina, חייבין במעשר, chayavin beMa'aser, are
obligated in מעשר, Ma'aser, even though they're very small. Okay, so we
had a statement by מעשר Ma'aser that they're still obligated in מעשר,
Ma'aser, and apparently this gets back to the idea of defining a
fruit, and do we assume the definition goes across categories?
So the first opinion said as long as these fruit are available,
you know, even if they're only the very small variety, that means
that you can still eat your figs. And רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
said back, no, those things might be big enough to be obligated
in מעשר, Ma'aser, but they're not considered the same type of figs
that you can eat your
figs
in the
home just because those are still available out on the tree. They
wouldn't want you to think that because they were small they weren't
yet ripe. There were some species that just, right, but רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, I don't think רב יהודה Rav Yehuda disagreed about whether
they were ripe, but he just disagreed about whether that's significant for
eating the larger varieties that you still have in your home. Okay,
so but yes, the purpose of that teaching by מעשר Ma'aser is
that they're still considered edible and they're still considered fruit for מעשר.
Ma'aser.
Now we go back with
they're like the little little little ones had a problem before.
Right, so that's this issue about about this question about being considered
a fruit. So אוכלין בתמרים עד שיכלה האחרון שבצוער. Ochlin biTmarim ad
sheyichla ha'acharon shebeTzoar. Now,
we just had this question about different stages, we're going to quote
back what we said yesterday about that the dates can be eaten
until there's none left in צוער. Tzoar. This is going back to
a ברייתא Beraita we quoted yesterday. So the dates go by the
last one in צוער. Tzoar. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer אוכלין אף על גב בין הקיפים ואף על גב
בין השיצין. Ochlin af al gav bein hakifim ve'af al gav bein
hashitzin. You can only eat as long as the dates can be
found sort of on or caught between the branches, but if the
only place the dates can be found out in the field is
in the on the ground between the thorns of the palm tree,
that's not good enough. That's not considered found or available because they're
inedible there and the animals don't have access to it. Okay, ורמינהי,
veraminihi, I'll ask you on this statement. So this says until the
until they're found in צוער. Tzoar. But we have another ברייתא Beraita
that tells you where you know how long you can eat the
dates and says the following: אוכלין בענבים עד הפסח. Ochlin be'anavim ad
haPesach.
You can eat grapes until פסח, Pesach, because they're available until פסח
Pesach time. Now I've got to tell you what's interesting about all
of these ברייתות Beraitot is they don't tell you are you talking
about יהודה Yehuda or גליל, Galil, right? Which one are you talking
about? We know that there's different rules between יהודה Yehuda and גליל,
Galil, there's different periods of time. So I don't know the answer.
Anyway, you can eat grapes until
פסח. Pesach. בזיתים עד העצרת, bezeitim ad haAtzeret, olives until
שבועות. Shavuot. בגרוגרות עד החנוכה. bigrogerot ad haChanukah. You can eat the
dried figs, thank you again, until חנוכה. Chanukah. בתמרים
עד הפורים, bitmarim ad haPurim, and dates, until פורים. Purim. Very convenient
that all these fruits ripen right you know stop being available right
around the holiday seasons. Good way to remember. So presumably what we're
dealing here anyway is exactly this is we're moving to try to
create simple dates on the calendar. So you don't dates, right, on
the calendar, even because there's a rule, but the rule is very
subjective and it's very year by year, so the Rabbis are trying
to simplify it a little bit and give you specific dates on
the calendar that you know by this date you should not be
eating dates anymore or olives anymore or grapes anymore. One minute. ואמר
רב ביבי Ve'amar Rav Bibi רבי יוחנן תרתי בתרייתא מחליף. Rabbi Yochanan
tarti batraita machlif.
רב ביבי Rav Bibi said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan swapped the last
two. He said that the... He said that the dried figs you
can go to פורים Purim and the dates until חנוכה, Chanukkah, which
is a big swap. I mean, there's a huge gap of time
between those two. Very hard to imagine like what you know, how
you could come up with such radically different dates. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara thinks that this is a problem. Why is this a
problem? It's a problem because here we say that the dates go
until what did we say? פורים Purim or חנוכה? Chanukkah? Whereas רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says it goes until they're
no longer available in צוער. Tzoar. So which one is it?
So the answer, it might be different geographic areas.
Well, that's true too. There could be יהודה Yehuda versus גליל, Galil,
but the גמרא Gemara has an easier answer. The גמרא Gemara says
אידי ואידי חד שיעורא הוא. idi ve'idi chad shiura hu. Alright, so
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel spoke in sort of
descriptive terms, it's no longer available in צוער, Tzoar, and this ברייתא
Braita translates it into a specific day on the calendar, but ultimately
they're talking about the same time. Roughly this day, חנוכה Chanukkah or
פורים, Purim, is when they're no longer available
in צוער. Tzoar. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'ibayit eima, and if you want I
can tell you, הכי קתני בהדיא, ha-katni ba-hedya, the ברייתא Braita we
talked before explicitly said, אם יש מאוחרות מהן אוכלים עליהן, im yesh
me-ucharot me-hen ochlim aleihen, that exactly this, that we'll try to give
you a general rule, right? But but it's not meant to actually
limit it to that time. You can always see if there's still
stuff available and out there later than this time, you're okay. So
the same way before we tried to give a rule about a
certain place, right? If they're in גוש חלב Gush Chalav or if
they're here or if they're there, you know, and but then we
said, but don't limit it to that place. If you can find
later ones, you can find. So here too it's the same basic
idea. We give you a particular date, but it doesn't mean that
that's the end of the story. If you can still find dates
in צוער, Tzoar, which is what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel said, then you can still continue to eat. So again
what's interesting here, I mean, it's all the principle of as long
as it's available out in the field. But what's interesting here, and
again this is something we've discussed and it came up particularly because
nowadays, you know, everybody thinks, oh, it's defined as חמץ chametz if
it's more than eighteen minutes, you know, outside of the oven or
whatever. When the גמרא Gemara that was one statement in one גמרא,
Gemara, but all of the other descriptions had to do with observing
it, you know, direct observation to see whether or not it became
חמץ. chametz. But people want quantifiable measurable ways of determining. So here
too, you know, we try to sort of more quantify it, dates
on the calendar, look at this place, look at that place, but
we still acknowledge that there's that it is more subjective and you
can in truth go by whenever every case by case as long
as something is still available out of the field. Yes.
But I think that may address the question I had. They've got
four of the five fruits there but they don't have pomegranate.
Oh, that's a good question. I have no idea.
But also is this talking about grapes for eating or grapes for
wine, and similarly for olives is it olives for eating or olives
for oil?
Oh, you mean if you've already converted the grapes into wine, would
you have to distribute the wine if it no longer existed as
a fruit? Right. Oh, that's an interesting question.
Because they talked earlier about שביעית shevi'it wine. Right.
Look, the I'm pretty sure it would apply regardless of the form
because the case earlier spoke about, if you remember, like pickling them
together, although anyway תוספות Tosafot said that was one of the issues
there when it wasn't the thing itself, but it was the taste
of the thing.
But here you're talking even more than just giving taste. You're talking
actually just the thing converted into a liquid. It's a good question.
But you wouldn't have wine on שביעית? shevi'it?
No you would, but would you be able to keep on drinking
your שביעית shevi'it wine? Actually, you'd be able
to keep on drinking your שביעית shevi'it wine when there's no longer
any grapes available out of the field? That actually is very relevant
because there is שביעית shevi'it wine. Right, but the question is whether
you סומך samach on the היתר מכירה heter mechira or
not. Because if you're not סומך somech on the היתר מכירה heter
mechira and you buy שביעית shevi'it wine, can you keep on drinking
it once there's no longer grapes out of the field? That's a
very good question.
Okay, we mentioned bread also there, שביעית shevi'it of the same thing
with
the grain in the field.
Yeah, it gets to a point in שבט, Shevat, you're
not gonna have bread?
Well again, it doesn't
mean you can't own it. What it means is you take it
out and you make it available again to all of your neighbors
and you call everybody and saying, yeah, I have all of this
stuff stored up, everybody come and take, and you can also take
back some of it, but just you just can't hoard it, you
know? It has to be now made available.
But at a certain point it's gonna run out, right? Right. Everybody,
and at a certain point it's possible at the beginning of the
eighth year you're not gonna have wine and you're not gonna have
חלה? challah?
Well look, in general that's an issue because people aren't planting so
there's a lot less that's being produced anyway, so it's stuff held
over from previous years, I guess. You know?
The bigger issue for grain, because grapes will keep growing, I mean
I'm sorry, mean you can have stuff, you can keep the stuff
from before שביעית. shevi'it.
Yeah, it's only שביעית shevi'it
produce that comes from the תורה, Torah,
so that's granted.
It was שביעית shevi'it produce, שביעית shevi'it שמן, shemen, right?
Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Okay. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר: Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer: סימן להרים מילין. Siman le-harim milin.
מילין, Milin, רש"י Rashi says, means a certain type of a of
a gallnut. three. Siman leamakim סימן לעמקים, Siman leamakim, a good sort
of a characteristic of valleys, siman סימן siman probably just means characteristic,
is dkalim דקלים, dkalim, is palm trees, right? You know, you go
down to the Dead Sea, you see all those palm trees, right?
So the low line in the valley. Siman lenachalim סימן לנחלים, Siman
lenachalim, wadi characteristic is kanim קנים, kanim, is bullrushes. Siman lishfela סימן
לשפלה, Siman lishfela, the lowlands, is shikma שקמה, shikma, is sycamore trees.
Ve'af al pi she'ein raya ladavar zecher ladavar ואף על פי שאין
ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר, Ve'af al pi she'ein raya ladavar zecher ladavar,
although there's no, there's you can't prove it, there's a hint to
it, shene'emar שנאמר, shene'emar, vayiten hamelech et hakesef b'Yerushalayim ka'avanim ויתן המלך
את הכסף בירושלים כאבנים, Vayiten hamelech et hakesef b'Yerushalayim ka'avanim, and Shlomo
made the silver in Jerusalem like stones, ve'et ha'arazim natan kashikmim asher
bashfela ואת הארזים נתן כשקמים אשר בשפלה, Ve'et ha'arazim natan kashikmim asher
bashfela, and the cedar trees were as plentiful as the sycamores in
the valley. So you see that I'm in the lowlands. So you
see that that the lowland is known by the sycamore trees. Larov
לרוב, Larov, they were so
plentiful. Siman leharim milin סימן להרים מילין, Siman leharim milin, so siman
leamakim dkalim סימן לעמקים דקלים, Siman leamakim dkalim, so what do I
care about the mountains and about the valleys? So nafa kamina le'bikurim
נפקא מינה לביכורים. Nafka mina le'bikurim. It's relevant for bikurim ביכורים, bikurim,
d'nan דתנן, d'nan, because you only bring bikurim ביכורים bikurim from the
shivat haminim שבעת המינים, shivat haminim, but also we taught in the
Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, ein mevi'im bikurim ela mishivat haminim אין מביאים ביכורים
אלא משבעת המינים, Ein mevi'im bikurim ela mishivat haminim, only from the
seven main, you know, types of the grain and the fruit. Velow
midkalim shebeharim ולא מדקלים שבהרים, Velow midkalim shebeharim, and even though you
bring from the palm trees from dates, it can't be from the
palm trees that grow up in the mountains, because those are not
the true palm trees. The true palm trees are the ones that
grow in the valley, in the amakim עמקים. amakim. Velow miperot sheba'amakim
ולא מפירות שבעמקים, Velow miperot sheba'amakim, similarly perot פירות perot here Rashi
רש"י Rashi says means like the wheat and the grains, it's not
the ones that grow in the valleys. So those, the best of
the wheats grow not in the valleys and the best of the
palm trees grow in the valleys. So therefore we said that valleys
and palm trees go together to tell you that that you only
bring from from palm trees that are in the valleys and you
don't bring from other things that are in the valleys because you
have to bring the best of both. Why we had to tell
me that mountains have these gallnut trees, I don't know. Siman lenachalim
kanim סימן לנחלים קנים. Siman lenachalim kanim. That's a wadi, you know?
I guess,
but now we have to explain everything else. So the wadis have
bullrushes. Nafa kamina lenachal eitan נפקא מינה לנחל איתן. Nafka mina lenachal
eitan. Because you're supposed to take the egla arufa עגלה ערופה egla
arufa to a to a wadi and the wadi cannot have been
you know sort of you know planted by people but it has
to have these bullrushes. If it doesn't have a bullrush it's not
considered to be like a paradigmatic wadi. So a wadi without bullrushes
does not halakhically define a wadi, which is a pretty wild idea.
Siman lishfela shikma סימן לשפלה שקמה, Siman lishfela shikma, how about this
idea of the lowlands is the sycamore? Nafa kamina lemikach umimkar נפקא
מינה למקח וממכר. Nafka mina lemikach umimkar. So yeah, the only relevance
would be in business, if you promise somebody that you're selling them
an area in the shfela שפלה shfela and there were no sycamores,
you couldn't really call that case place the shfela שפלה shfela if
there were no sycamores around. Hashta de'atat lehachi השתא דאתית להכי, Hashta
de'atat lehachi, now that we gave business as a relevant example, not
example, application of this rule, kuluna nami lemikach umimkar כולהו נמי למקח
וממכר. Kuluna nami lemikach umimkar.
Everything could be relevant to mikach umimkar מקח וממכר. mikach umimkar. If
I say I'm selling you mountain and there's no gallnut trees you
really can't call the thing a mountain, which is pretty funny. Okay,
that you'd need all of those things to give them that that
identity.
Oh, what if I say, you know, you contract with me to
buy, you know, dates or whatever it is, you
know, and they have to be from... No, that we wouldn't say.
That's only by bikurim ביכורים bikurim it has to be the best
dates. He's saying the opposite, that for this place to be called
the place, or not the opposite, but emphasizing for it to be
called the place it needs these characteristics. Okay, now we move on
back to the makom shenahagu מקום שנהגו makom shenahagu and actually get
to a very
fascinating aspect about this relating to Pesach פסח. Pesach. Although as you
can see we're not limiting ourselves to Pesach פסח Pesach issues. Makom
shenahagu limkor behema daka lenochrim mocharim מקום שנהגו למכור בהמה דקה לנוכרים
מוכרים. Makom shenahagu limkor behema daka lenochrim mocharim. Place where they will
sell, now this is a Mishnah משנה Mishnah also in Avodah Zarah
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and the Gemara גמרא Gemara is not going
to discuss it at all here because it gets discussed in Avodah
Zarah עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but the last line it will discuss.
The last line gets back to Pesach פסח. Pesach. So basically according
to the Gemara גמרא Gemara in Avodah עבודה Avodah there was a
practice not to sell large animals, cows or horses to the non-Jew.
But they would sell in some places the small grazing animals like
the sheep and the goats. Now the reason for this is never
spelled out in the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. The Gemara גמרא, Gemara, there
might be different Bavli בבלי-Yerushalmi Bavli ירושלמי Yerushalmi how they understand it,
but the Bavli בבלי Bavli understands that the concern is a Shabbat
שבת Shabbat concern. That if I sell you a cow or a
horse, that's okay. But if I rented you a cow or a
horse, or I let you borrow it because you know you were
deciding whether or not to buy it and then on Shabbat שבת
Shabbat you were riding or using my cow or horse because it
was still mine, you didn't buy it yet, then I would be
letting my animal work on Shabbat שבת. Shabbat. So we didn't let
people sell cows or horses to non-Jews because they would come to
rent them or loan them to them. Now that seems like a
pretty big concern, you know issue, and it's possible to understand that
it was not limited to a Shabbat שבת Shabbat concern. It might
have had other concerns about just in general if you learn Masechet
מסכת Masechet Avodah Zarah עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah you see the question...
Exactly how much you want to sort of protect the things that
are central to, you know, exactly how much you want to sort
of protect the things that are central to to to sort of
the Land of Israel and keep them under Jewish control, you know,
things that are about sort of like taking having
control over the land. So anyway, מקום שנהגו למכור בהמה דקה לנכרים
מוכרים. makom shenagu limkor behema daka lenochrim mocherim. But if you, so
where they sold these grazing animals, you can sell them. מקום שלא
נהגו למכור, makom shelo nagu limkor, or the better גרסא girsa is
שנהגו שלא למכור. shenagu shelo limkor. If you had the place that
you had the practice not to sell, even grazing animals, which didn't
have as much of a concern of being borrowed, אין מוכרין. ein
mocherin. But if you extended it to the grazing animals, some people
extended it, so in those places you would not be allowed to
sell the grazing animals. Yeah,
there is an issue of
גידול בהמה דקה בארץ ישראל. gidul behema daka b'Eretz Yisrael.
There is actually, it actually ruins the land. Yeah, there actually is.
Separate. Yeah, I mean how right, but how exactly you could be
having these grazing animals or what happens to the whole problem about
being raising grazing animals is a good question.
And they raised the animals for the קרבנות. korbanot. Right.
The answer is, I'm not going to tell you. ובכל מקום אין
מוכרין להם. uvchol makom ein mocherin lahem. But every place agrees in
all places you can't sell them, בהמה גסה, behema gassa, large animals
like cows or horses and not only when they're adults, but even
עגלים וסיחין, agalim vesiyachin, even calves and foals you can't sell even
though those won't be able to be used for מלאכה melacha right
away, even presumably if the concern is that they'll be used by
the non-Jews to do מלאכה melacha on שבת Shabbat when they're being
loaned out, and so even though that's not relevant for the small
ones, it's still a problem. We made the whole category. And not
only that, שלמים ושבורים, shlemim ushvurim, whether they are whole, meaning uninjured,
or even injured, even with like a broken leg, even though you
could say nobody's going to use it if it's got a broken
leg. Nevertheless, we forbid the whole category. רבי יהודה מתיר בשבורה. Rabbi
Yehuda matir bishvura. Rabbi Yehuda says
the one with a broken leg is okay because they'll שחט shecht
it right away. So it's not going to lead to the idea
of our animals in their possession, it'll be שחטed shecht right away.
בן בתירא מתיר בסוס. Ben Beteira matir besus. Ben Beteira allowed horses
to be sold to non-Jews. Why? So again, you could focus here
not like the גמרא בעבודה זרה Gemara b'Avodah Zarah that it's an
issue about שבת Shabbat concerns, but it's an issue about, you know,
what's this word I'm looking for, husbanding is I guess the word
I'm looking for, the land, you know, who basically is controlling the
agriculture of the land and who has not only the land itself
but who has the cows and the horses and so on, the
things that help you cultivate the land. So from that perspective, horses
are not so much about cultivating the land as cows are, right?
They're about plowing and so on. They're about getting around, but they're
not about cultivating the land. The גמרא Gemara though, that focuses on
the שבת Shabbat concerns, says even if the non-Jew was using my
horse to ride on on שבת, Shabbat, it wouldn't actually technically be
a violation of my animal doing מלאכה melacha because we have a
principle of חי נושא את עצמו, chai nosei et atzmo, that a
living person carries some of their own weight, and therefore the horse
would not be, that's why even like carry a baby on שבת,
Shabbat, you know, or carry another human on שבת, Shabbat, you know,
there's a question about when is a baby maybe at a so
small still considered dead weight, but anyway, you don't biblically violate because
a person supports, you know, once somebody is dead actually, they're harder
to carry. Now the actual reason I found out for this is
not that a person literally lifts their own weight, but that if
a person as long as they're alive, even if they're unconscious, their
body is automatically providing, balancing itself, and when they're dead, it's providing
no balance, so it's much harder to carry. But that idea anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says is you don't violate שבת Shabbat by carrying
a live person, so therefore the horse that's not allowed to do
מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbat, right, בהמתך, behemtecha, you have to not
let your animals do מלאכה melacha also would not be a problem
when they're carrying a live person. So therefore
Ben Beteira says therefore you can rent them, you can sell them
horses. Of course, what about the fact that sometimes you have saddlebags
on your horses and you don't have people riding on it? I
don't know the answer. Anyway, okay. מקום Makom now, that all is
discussed in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, we're not discussing it here. מקום
שנהגו, Makom shenagu, now we get to a very interesting point about
by פסח. Pesach. מקום שנהגו לאכול צלי בלילי פסחים אוכלים. Makom shenagu
le'echol tzali beleilei Pesachim ochlim. The place where they have the custom
to eat roasted meat on פסח Pesach night on the סדר Seder
night, you eat it. מקום שנהגו שלא לאכול אין אוכלים. Makom shenagu
shelo le'echol ein ochlim. A place where you have a custom not
to eat it, you don't eat it. Now, what do you think
here is the מנהג? minhag? Meaning, you know, what is the norm
and what's the מנהג? minhag? Meaning normally
right, there's a special מנהג, minhag, we don't sell small, you know,
grazing
animals. We, we don't do מלאכה melacha even the morning of ערב
פסח. Erev Pesach. So what here would you assume is the מנהג
minhag and what is sort of just the סתם stam practice? So
you think,
so you assume the מנהג minhag is we're מקפיד makpid not to
eat roasted meat. Right, so that's how
אשכנזים. Ashkenazim. Right, so from an אשכנזי *Ashkenazi* perspective we know, oh,
the הלכה *halacha* is you're not allowed to eat roasted meat. So
if this was like, some people say they don't care, they'll eat
whatever, they'll even eat roasted meat, but we have a מנהג minhag
*minhag* not to eat roasted meat so it shouldn't look like we're
eating a קרבן korban *korban* outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*. Right. So
that's what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says. If you look at רש"י *Rashi*,
שלא יאכלו דמחזי ככוחל פסח Pesach. בחוץ bachutz. *shelo yochlu d'mechzi ke'ochel
Pesach bachutz*. It looks like you're eating קרבן korban *korban* out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*. But if you ask ספרדים *Sefardim*, do you know
anybody know what some ספרדי *Sefardi* מנהגים *minhagim* are for סדר *Seder*
night?
דוקא dafka *Dafka* have roasted meat and some דוקא dafka *davka* have
roasted lamb, okay, or roasted goat, זכר לפסח *zecher lePesach*. So you
could read the end of the משנה Mishnah *mishna* the opposite way,
that the מנהג *minhag* is to דוקא dafka *davka*, if you have
a מנהג *minhag* to דוקא *davka* eat roasted meat, okay, that's your
מנהג *minhag*. If you don't have a מנהג *minhag* to do it,
so fine, you don't have to eat roasted meat. It's not that
the מנהג *minhag* is not to eat the meat, it's that you're
not מקפיד machpid *makpid* to eat roasted meat. So it's very interesting,
this question, there could be an argument that you דוקא *davka* should,
זכר לפסח *zecher lePesach*, and an argument that you דוקא *davka* should
not, because it's a problem to do too much of a זכר
לפסח *zecher lePesach*. It looks like you're eating a קרבן Korban *korban*.
That exact tension plays out,
like a thousand years after the, well,
things don't just start a thousand years after. All right, I don't
know, let's take a look now at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that
exact tension plays out in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. אמר amar, רב
יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda Amar Rav *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*,
אסור לאדם שיאמר בשר זה basar zeh לפסח *assur le'adam sheyomar basar
zeh lePesach*. A person cannot say to the meat they're having on
the סדר *Seder* night, oh, this is for the פסח Pesach. *Pesach*.
מפני שנראה כמקדיש בהמתו ואוכל קדשים בחוץ kodashim bachutz. *mipnei shenireh kemakdish
behematov ve'ochel kodshim bachutz*. It looks like you had sanctified your animal
and that you're actually eating meat of a קרבן *korban*, which is
why when we say, right, פסח Pesach מצה מרור *Pesach matzah maror*,
we don't say פסח Pesach. זה *Pesach zeh*. We say פסח Pesach.
שהיו אבותינו אוכלים *Pesach shehayu avoteinu ochlim*. Okay, now this again is
a statement that רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says in the name of
רב *Rav*. So he says we're particularly מקפיד *makpid* to מחמיר *machmir*
and מקפיד *makpid* to avoid too much things looking like it might
be part of the קרבן פסח korban Pesach, *korban Pesach*. So for
him, that's the emphasis, to keep your distance from things that look
like קרבן פסח korban Pesach *korban Pesach*. אמר amar רב פפא *Amar
Rav Pappa*, דוקא בשר *davka basar*. That's only for meat, to say
this meat is for the פסח Pesach *Pesach*. Okay, meaning even if
you're going to the butcher store, you can't say, oh, I'm going
to buy these steaks לפסח *lePesach*. I don't know if you really
can't say that, but is it true? Yeah, it's a question whether
right, because פסח *Pesach* means the יום טוב *Yom Tov* and פסח
*Pesach* means the קרבן פסח korban Pesach *korban Pesach*. So it might
be that he's not just saying the meat you're having on the
סדר *Seder* night, even at the butcher store you can't say, but
I don't know anybody who's מקפיד *makpid* on that, right?
You could say that on I'm going to have a סדר *Seder*
night, then, then it'd be.
No, it's לפסח *lePesach* makes it for the קרבן פסח korban Pesach
*korban Pesach*. But anyway, it's the word לפסח *lePesach*. אבל חטי לא
lo, *aval chitey lo*. But you can say this wheat is for
פסח *Pesach* because obviously you're not going to make wheat into a
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach, *korban Pesach*. And anyway, לנטור להו לפיסחא אמר
*lentur lehu lepischa amar*. It means I'm going to watch them for
פסח *Pesach* to make sure that they don't get wet and they
don't become חמץ *chametz*.
Okay, now when you say פסח *Pesach* also, you don't mean
a קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*, you mean. I know, but the problem
with רב *Rav* might be saying is that the meat could be
interpreted otherwise. The wheat you don't interpret otherwise. Yeah, it's a big
question. Fine. ובשר לא *u'vasar lo*. Is it really true that you
can't do it by meat? מתיבי *meitivei*. I'll ask you. אמר רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosei *Amar Rabbi Yosi*, תודוס איש רומי Tudos ish Romi
הנהיג את בני רומי *Todus Ish Romi hinhig et bnei Romi*. תודוס
Tudos. *Todus* was a very important person in Rome. We'll feel a
little bit about him in a minute. He started a practice, must
be about מנהג *minhag* here, in Rome, לאכול גדיים מקולסין בלילי פסחים
*le'echol gedayim mekulasin beleilei pesachim*. So notice the issue of מנהג *minhag*.
The מנהג *minhag* was דוקא *davka* to have a pseudo-פסח *Pesach* on
the פסח *Pesach* night. They would take goat and מקולס mekulas *mekulas*
means they would roast it whole over an open fire, exactly like
you would do by קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*. ראשו על כרעיו ועל
קרבו *rosho al kra'av ve'al kirbo*. So he had the מנהג *minhag*
to do a whole pseudo-פסח *Pesach* on פסח *Pesach* night in Rome.
שלחו לו *shalechu lo*. The rabbis sent to him a message, אלמלא
תודוס Tudos אתה *ilmaleh Todus attah*. Were you not such an important
person, תודוס Tudos *Todus*, were you not who you are, גזרנו עליך
נידוי *gazarnu alecha niduy*, we'd put you in חרם cherem? *cherem* for
doing this, שאתה מאכיל את ישראל קדשים בחוץ bachutz *she'atah ma'achil et
Yisrael kodshim bachutz*, that you're making them eat קרבנות *korbanot* outside the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
קדשים סלקא דעתך *kodshim saktaitach*? Literally
קרבנות *korbanot*? Is that really קרבנות *korbanot*? אלא אימא קרוב להאכיל ישראל
קדשים בחוץ *ela eima karov le'hachil Yisrael kodshim bachutz*. It looks like
it's almost as if you're making them eat it. Okay, so you
see that you're not allowed to do it. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, מקולס אין *mekulas in*. The problem was that he went
too far. He made it like roasted the whole thing, the entire
animal. שאינו מקולס לא *she'eino mekulas lo*. But if the whole thing
wasn't roasted, even if you had סתם *stam* roasted meat and certainly
if you just had סתם *stam* meat, there would not be this
problem that it looks too much like a קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, no, אמרי *amri*, you can say,
מקולס *mekulas*, if you're roasting it whole, לא שנא אמר לא שנא
לא אמר *lo shena amar lo shena lo amar*. It doesn't matter
whether you verbally say this is for the פסח *Pesach* or not.
The fact that you're roasting it whole already makes it very problematic.
שאינו מקולס *she'eino mekulas*, if it's not מקולס *mekulas*, פירש אין *pireish
in*, only if you explicitly say זה לפסח *zeh lePesach*. לא פירש
לא *lo pireish lo*, if you didn't explicitly say you're okay. So
one or the other's a problem if it looks too much like
a קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*, either that you roast it whole or
you explicitly. specifically designated as such. But again I want you to
see the tension. You have some approach that says that the concern
is the practice has to be not to make too much look
like the קרבן פסח, if not don't have roasted meat, certainly don't
have, you know, מקולס goats, you know, and don't say it's the
פסח. And the other push is דוקא to have something that is
a pseudo פסח. Now if you were reading this, the impression you
would leave with is that Theodosius was completely rejected, and that practice
is completely unacceptable, and the idea is דוקא he would read the
משנה Mishnah, that the practice is not to have roasted meat. But
as I already pointed out, if people know מנהג ספרדים minhag Sefardim
is to have roasted meat, and there's evidence in other משניות Mishnayot
and in another תוספתא Tosefta that some actual of the תנאים Tannaim
had, were מקפיד to have really like roasted meat on פסח and
actually went so far as calling it perhaps a קרבן פסח, okay,
or calling it a פסח. So this idea that you can't call
it this and you can't do this or whatever, you know, this
is like there's pushes both ways and we shouldn't believe just from
this גמרא Gemara just because it starts with the statement of רב
יהודה אמר רב that the other approach which is דוקא to have
roasted meat was completely, you know, rejected. That might be exactly the
other approach mentioned in the משנה, Mishnah, the מנהג to have roasted
meat on פסח. Okay, so let's continue now in the גמרא. Gemara
רמי בר חמא מתני להא מתניתא לרבי שמעון. Remi bar Chama matni
leha matnita lerabbi Shimon.
So or so he taught this ברייתא baraita that said that they
criticized Theodosius in the name of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Right, we
had it before that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei said they criticized Theodosius.
He said that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said it. מתקיף לה רב
ששת, Matkif lah Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet asked this. בשלמא
למן דתני לה כרבי יוסי, Bishlama leman de-tani lah kerabbi Yosei, I
get it if it's said in the name of רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosei that he told the story about Theodosius and that he was
criticized, ניחא, nicha, that works. אלא למן דמתני כרבי שמעון, Ella leman
de-matni kerabbi Shimon, but if you said in the name of רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, מי ניחא? minicha? Why, how is that good? והתנן,
Ve-hatnan, that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say that Theodosius was criticized.
Why is that a problem? Cause we taught in a משנה, רבי
שמעון פוטר שלא התנדב כדרך המתנדבים. Rabbi Shimon poter she-lo hitnadev kederekh
ha-mitnadvim. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
exempts because a person did not make a normal type of a
vow. What does this mean? So the case is somebody said, took
a vow and said I'm obligating myself to bring a מנחה mincha
from
barley. Now a מנחה mincha that is a vowed מנחה, mincha, the
only מנחה mincha from barley basically is a סוטה. Sotah. The מנחה
mincha that is a vowed מנחה mincha can only be from wheat.
So what do you do with a statement that's nonsensical? I'm obligating
myself to bring a מנחה mincha from wheat—from barley. So some say,
well, we'll make it sensical and we'll cut off the last two
words from barley and we'll say that he's obligating himself to bring
a מנחה. mincha. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, we look at
his whole statement, his whole statement is meaningless, we don't force it
to make meaning and he's exempt, he's exempt from bringing anything. Now
how's that relevant here? Because the way תוספות Tosafot understands, I'll skip
רש״י, Rashi, the way תוספות Tosafot understands is we're concerned that Theodosius
was having these גדיים מקולסים, gediyim mekulasim, he says oh it'll look
like people have sanctified these animals for קרבן פסח and brought them
בחוץ. He said oh, but according to רבי יוסי—I'm Rebbi Yosi, sorry,
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon if you
said בשר זה—you said, you know, this animal I'm מקדיש, makdish, you
explicitly said I'm מקדיש makdish for קרבן פסח to bring it here
and roast. Okay, so if you said that, it wouldn't have קדושה
kedusha because there's no such thing as a קרבן פסח brought outside
of ירושלים, the same way there's no such thing as a מנחה
mincha of barley, there's no such thing as a פסח out of
ירושלים.
Ever, ever over then on the—it's קדשים בחוץ. You'd say alright I'm
מקדיש makdish it בחוץ but there's no value.
You could be מקדיש—there makdish isn't an איסור issur to be מקדיש
בחוץ, makdish bachutz, there's an איסור issur to be מקריב בחוץ. makriv
bachutz. Okay, so you could be מקדיש סתם makdish stam and then
מקריב בחוץ. makriv bachutz. But if you were מקדיש makdish for the
sake of bringing it outside of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. according
to him if you explicitly said I'm being מקדיש makdish this to
bring in Rome, then for him it would have no קדושה. kedusha.
So the גמרא says according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he shouldn't
be so bothered about what Theodosius does. Now of course for you
and me we're looking at what Theodosius does and we're not concerned
about whether people actually were מקדיש makdish or not, right, to us
it still looked like way too close to the real thing and
you shouldn't be doing it out of the בית המקדש. But according
to the גמרא as long as maybe as long as no—it's not
possible for that to have really to have been a קרבן it
shouldn't have been a problem.
Right, I think רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying something very deep
here, he's saying as—you know that the reality historically makes it impossible,
right,
therefore
it's impossible to take his language in any way other than metaphorical
and that religious experience requires that metaphorical language.
So yeah, as you said much better than I could, that is
correct. So that's what it says, according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
if the—if it's not a meaningful statement, it's not binding, so it's
impossible for this to have really have been a קרבן so it
shouldn't have been a problem. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar leh
Ravina le-Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said back to רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, you think we can't have—רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would be okay
with this? ומן דמתני לה כרבי יוסי מי ניחא? U-man de-matni lah
kerabbi Yosei minicha? But... According to רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi. you think
it's okay because he didn't say the רב שמעון Reb Shimon statement?
So it shouldn't be good even according to רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi.
Why? ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, רב שמעון בשיטת רבי יוסי אמרה, Reb
Shimon b'shittas Reb Yosi amrah, דאמר, di-amar,
because רבא Rava says in that case when a person says, I'm
bringing a מנחה Mincha from barley, that רב שמעון Reb Shimon is
saying two things. Number one is I'm willing to take his, not
edit his statement, meaning I'm willing to say even if his statement
is nonsensical, as opposed to making it make sense, I'll just throw
the whole thing out. That's רב שמעון's Reb Shimon point. לא נתכוון
זה אלא כמתנדב, lo nisnaven zeh ela k'misnadev,
אמר, okay throwing the whole statement out, not trying to make it
make sense. But part of what he's also saying is a position
of רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi There's a debate that if somebody says
something that's contradictory, do you end his sentence early or do you
look at the end of the sentence? So for example, if somebody
said, this animal is an עולה שלמים, Olah Shelamim, or an עולה,
Olah, you know, so it can't be both an עולה Olah and
a שלמים. Shelamim. So there are those that say, so stop his
sentence at the word עולה. Olah. There's רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi that
says בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס. bi-gmar devarav adam nitpas. No, you have
to include the end of the sentence. So how could something be
an עולה שלמים? Olah Shelamim? Okay, it's sanctified for both and you
have to sell it and use half the proceeds for one, half
the proceeds for the other.
So that's the statement that, so there's רב שמעון's Reb Shimon idea
is two points. Number one is I look at your whole statement,
and number two is, even as opposed to the עולה שלמים Olah
Shelamim case, which is a case where you could satisfy it by
making it half and half, this case you'd have to throw the
whole thing out because there's no such thing as a קרבן בחוץ,
Korban be-chutz, there's no such thing as a מנחה Mincha out of,
out of barley. But I'm okay with that. I'm okay to look
at the whole statement and then to throw everything out, rather than
to try to take half of it to make sense of it.
So that's רב שמעון Reb Shimon holds like רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi,
that you look at the end of the statement. So he says,
so he says, מאי לאו, mai lav, can we not infer, מדאמר
רב שמעון סבר לה כרבי יוסי, mi-de-Reb Shimon savar lah k'Rebbi Yosi,
since רב שמעון Reb Shimon holds of רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi רבי
יוסי נמי סבר לה כרב שמעון, Rebbi Yosi nami savar lah k'Reb
Shimon, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi would hold of רב שמעון Reb Shimon
and say you look at the whole statement and you would throw
it out if you have to. And therefore even רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosi. shouldn't have had a problem with תודוס. Todos והגמרא אומרת Ve-ha-gemara
omeret לא, no, רב שמעון סבר לה כרבי יוסי, Reb Shimon savar
lah k'Rebbi Yosi, רב שמעון Reb Shimon does hold like רבי יוסי.
Rebbi Yosi This is a very easy to misread this line. You
could read it לא רב שמעון סבר, lo Reb Shimon savar, but
no, you're wrong. רב שמעון סבר לה כרבי יוסי, Reb Shimon savar
lah k'Rebbi Yosi, רב שמעון Reb Shimon holds like רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosi that you do look at the end of the statement, ורבי
יוסי לא סבר לה כרב שמעון, v'Rebbi Yosi lo savar lah k'Reb
Shimon, but רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi does not hold of רב שמעון,
Reb Shimon, which means yes, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi says you look
at the statement, but if you're able to make sense of the
whole thing. But if you would have to throw the whole sentence
out, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi would say then you truncate it. Okay,
so רבי יוסי is not prepared to throw out a statement that
doesn't make sense. So it's only רב שמעון Reb Shimon who says
that if somebody says I'm sanctifying this animal to bring it as
a קרבן here in Rome, that it's a non-meaningful statement and the
animal is not sanctified. Okay, so the גמרא says, ends by saying
that according to רב שמעון, Reb Shimon, he shouldn't have had such
a problem with what תודוס did because even though it looks like
a קרבן פסח, there's no way it could really have been that.
Okay, so now the גמרא ends by saying the following. איבעיא להו,
Ibayya lehu, they raised the question, תודוס איש רומי גברא רבא הוה,
Tudos ish Romi gavra rabba hava, this תודוס that they didn't want
to put in חרם? cherem? Why did they not want to put
him in חרם? cherem Was it because he was an important person?
Like, you know, sort of important in the eyes of the רבנים,
Rabbanim, maybe a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham or something? או בעל
אגרופין הוה, o baal egrofin hava, or maybe he was just a
powerful person like some mafioso and they didn't want to put him
in חרם cherem? because they didn't want to, they were afraid to
put him in חרם? cherem. Which one was it? תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear, עוד זו דרש תודוס איש רומי, Od zu
darash Tudos ish Romi, we have a ברייתא Braita that says that
תודוס איש רומי made the following additional דרשה, drasha, not clear what
the first דרשה drasha was, right, so basically he's making a דרשה,
drasha, so he's an important in the front, you know, he's important
as a, as a scholar, as a sage. What was his דרשה?
drasha? So מה ראו
חנניה
מישאל ועזריה שמסרו עצמם על קדושת השם,
mah rau
Chananiah Mishael va-Azariah she-masru atzmam al kedushas ha-Shem, what made חנניה מישאל
ועזריה Chananiah Mishael and Azariah see, what motivated them to be willing
to give up their lives to get themselves thrown into the oven
in the story with נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, in the fire, לכבשן האש? le-kivshan
ha-eish? So נשאו קל וחומר בעצמן, nas'u kal va-chomer b'atzman,
they made a קל וחומר kal va-chomer מצפרדעים, mi-tzfarde'im, from the frogs
in the story with פרעה, Pharaoh, the plague. ומה צפרדעים שאין מצווין
על קדושת השם, u-mah tzfarde'im she-ein mitzuavin al kedushas ha-Shem,
frogs that aren't commanded to sanctify God's name, כתיב בהו ובאו בביתך
ובחדר משכבך ועל מטתך ובבית עבדיך ובעמך ובתנוריך
ובמשארותיך, kesiv behu u-vau b'veisecha u-v'cheder mishkavecha v'al mitasecha u-v'veis avadecha u-v'amecha
u-v'tanurecha u-v'misharosecha, they'll come into your house and into your ovens and
into your kneading troughs. אימתי משארות
מצויות אצל תנור, eimasai misharos metzuyos eitzel tannur, when are kneading troughs
by the oven? בשעה שהתנור חם, b'sha'ah she-ha-tannur cham, when you're baking
bread and when the oven is hot. הוי אומר בשעה שהתנור חם,
hevei omer b'sha'ah she-ha-tannur cham, when the oven is hot. So they,
the frogs went into a hot oven, they threw themselves into the
fiery furnace just like חנניה מישאל ועזריה Chananiah Mishael and Azariah because
God said so. אנו שמצווים על קדושת השם, anu she-mitzuavin al kedushas
ha-Shem, we have an obligation to sanctify God's name, על אחת כמה
וכמה, al achas kamma v'khamma, how much more so. Now רש"י says
the question is how did they just know to give up their,
their lives rather than be עובד עבודה זרה? oved avodah zarah? תוספות
Tosafot says you don't need a big קל וחומר kal va-chomer for
that, of course you give up your life rather than עובד. oved.
The source has two other reads of it: either bowing down to
the idol that נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar was demanding of people wasn't really an
idol, it was just a statue, and even that they weren't willing
to do. They felt it was important to give up their lives
for קידוש השם kiddush Hashem even though it wasn't עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. Or תוספות Tosafot says they maybe could have escaped and they
chose not to escape and they chose to give up their lives.
Now these two answers, חיים סולובייצ'יק Chaim Soloveitchik I think and others
have already pointed out, could very interestingly be read through the historical
realities that תוספות Tosafot lived with in the Crusades, because Jews in
the Crusades in אשכנז Ashkenaz gave up their lives sometimes for things
that weren't הלכתית halachically יהרג ואל יעבור, yehareg ve'al ya'avor, but they
weren't הלכתית halachically obligated. It wasn't, you know, real things like do
it or you have to be עובד עבודה זרה. oved avoda zara.
They were willing to give up their lives, and sometimes they did
it even though they could have escaped and they were willing to
martyr themselves. So תוספות Tosafot reads into this story that that's the
decision חנניה מישאל ועזריה Hananiah Mishael ve'Azariah made, that they were... and
it's considered קידוש השם kiddush Hashem even though they could have escaped
and even if it wasn't real עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay, so
it's very interesting to read this מדרש Midrash through a lens of
the realities that תוספות Tosafot lived through. Is he allowed to give
up his life? That's the debate. Is there a concept of optional
קידוש השם? kiddush Hashem? When you give up your
life for God's honor even though it's not the big three, is
that basically considered
like a type of a suicide? If it's not commanded then it's
forbidden, or is there this category of optional קידוש השם? kiddush Hashem?
And תוספות Tosafot believes that there was a category of optional קידוש
השם, kiddush Hashem, and that's what he's reading into this story. The
גמרא ends the following way: רבי יוסי בר אבין Rabbi Yose bar
Avin אמר מטיא מליא לכיסא דתלמידי חכמים הוה. matya malya le'kisa de'talmidei
chachamim havah.
I'll tell you who תודוס was. He was somebody that basically made
investments for the תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Okay, so he basically helped
them in business. He got them jobs. He took some of their
money and invested it wisely for them. Alright, and that's what he
did. So you don't want to criticize some of your big donors,
okay? They might be doing something wrong, but we're not going to
criticize our big donors in public. Okay.
דאמר רבי יוחנן, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says what?
They put him in חרם. That's
true. דאמר רבי יוחנן de'amar Rabbi Yochanan כל המטיל מלאי לכיס תלמידי
חכמים, kol hamatil melai le'kis talmidei chachamim, anybody that basically puts some
filler into the wallet of תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, meaning basically helps
them invest their money, זוכה ויושב בישיבה של מעלה zoche ve'yoshev bi'yeshiva
shel ma'ala will ultimately sit in the heavenly... so that rich person
that helped out the תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, he'll merit that he'll
sit in the academy up above when they're in the world to
come. He'll be learning תורה Torah together with the תלמידי חכמים, talmidei
chachamim, שנאמר shene'emar כי בצל החכמה בצל הכסף, ki betzel hachochma betzel
hakesef, in the shade of wisdom is the shade of money. So
if you provided the money, you will ultimately merit in the shade
of wisdom. So anybody here who wants to be זוכה zoche in
that, please let me know. I have some money that I'd like
to
invest. Okay.